Guide to the Thomas Family Papers, 1895-1968
Department of Special Collections
Thomas Family Papers,
1895-1968
Special Collections M0260
Thomas family
4 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mary Denison Wilt Thomas, 1973, 1981 and 1983, and James D. Adams, 1981 and 1983.
Biographical Note: Jerome and Denison Thomas
Jerome Beers Thomas, Jr., who came from a prominent family in Brooklyn, New York, was the son of a physician who had served in the Civil War. The date of birth of Jerome Thomas, Jr., is unknown, but it is known that he followed his father into medicine. Where young Thomas attended medical school is also unknown, but his specialty was eye, ear, nose, and throat.
Mary Dension Wilt and Dr. Jerome Beers Thomas, Jr., had been married four years when he was sent in 1900 to the Philippine Islands as a contract surgeon for the U.S. Army. According to Denison, as she was called, Jerome had offered his services to the Navy when the war with Spain was declared in the spring of 1898, but the boats made him too sick and he transferred his services to the Army. Although the Spanish-American War ended in December 1898, The United States still maintained an Army presence after the war in the Islands with the dual mission of putting down insurrection, which had reasserted itself after the peace treaty was signed, and of seeing that the U.S. Commission established under the treaty could go about its work in relative safety while preparing the Philippines for democratic self-government after its 300 years as a Spanish colony.
Denison Wilt was born in Dayton, Ohio, and was graduated from Wellesley College in Massachusetts. By her own account, she was an avid student and a keen member of the women's rowing crew. She also developed a precise talent for sketching and watercolor painting. She cheerfully said goodbye to her husband when she learned of his new posting to the Philippines, knowing that she could soon join him, now that formal hostilities had ended.
Jerome left from New York for the Philippines, traveling east by Army transport to Gibralter, Port Said, Suez, Ceylon, and Singapore to Manila. Denison sailed from San Francisco a few weeks later, also by Army transport ship, sailing by way of Hawaii and Japan to Manila. Their first home in the Philippines was at Angeles, not far from Manila. From there, Jerome was sent to Apalit, where he became so popular among the villagers that the Filipinos name a street after him. While Jerome was occupied treating civilians and soldiers, the latter mainly for dengue fever and dysentery contracted in their campaigns to root out insurrection, Denison maintained her house, studied Spanish, grew to know the people, and explored the countryside, her camera and pencil always at the ready. She made friends wherever she went and was rarely without company. A frequent companion was Miss Mercy Brett, Jerome's cousin, who had come out to the Islands with Denison on leave from her job in Ohio at a Soldier's Home.
From Apalit, Jerome was sent to Taglibaran (Bohol Province), where he served not only in the field hospital but joined the troops occasionally on their sorties into the hills after guerillas. He was given a commission in the U. S. Army as a Captain, and in March 1902 was rushed to Manila to help combat an epidemic of cholora. Later that year, the Thomases were among those sent to Baguio (Benguet Province), when the mountain village was transformed, with Army help, into the Philippine summer capital, owing to its cooler altitidues, away from Manila's stifling summer heat. Here, Jerome oversaw the building of a large, modern hospital and was named to be its director at its completion. Baguio remained the Thomas's home until they returned to the United States in 1905.
Denison and Jerome Thomas enjoyed the friendship of a number of highly placed U.S. officials in the Philippines, including High Commissioner, and later Governor General, William Howard Taft, formerly a judge in Cincinnati, Ohion, and his successor, Luke C. Wright. Commissioners Henry Clay Ide, Bernard Moses, and in particular, Dean C. Worcester and his family, were also their friends. These connections brought the young couple into the white-linen-suit circles typical of the upper ends of society in several tropical countries of the period that were under foreign protectorates. As a consequence, the Thomas letters contain many references to dinner parties, balls, picnics, and horseback trips into the bush. But along with these diversions of their circle of friends, the Thomases were genuinely interested in U.S. and Philippine relations and in their surroundings and friends among the Filipinos and native peoples of the Islands. They spent many hours recording their experiences in writing, sketching, and photographing what they saw and heard.
Details of the Thomas's life on their return to the United States are few. It appears that Jerome resumed his practice in the New York, from late 1905 to 1910, when he became ill, and was advised by his physicians to seek a warmer climate. The couple chose California, living in Santa Cruz for a time, and then settling in Palo Alto in 1913. Jerome became a well-respected physician in his specialty, practicing until 1917. Dension took an active role in civic affairs, becoming one of two women to first be elected to the Palo Alto City Council in 1919-1923. During her tenure she was instrumental in the City's acquistion of some 930 acres of bayside marshland, and after her City Council days, she served on Palo Alto's Planning Commission. She was a member of the Sierra Club, and, although the couple had no children, she was very active in the Parent-Teacher Association. Both Denison and Jerome served on the Palo Alto Board of Public Safety. In World War I, they were active in Belgian War Relief, and on the Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies in World War II.
The couple lived at 1432 Webster Street in Palo Alto. Jerome died in 1948, and Denison, a charter member of the retirement community of Channing House, died on July 1, 1983, at the age of 108.
Scope and Content
The Thomas Family Papers collection consists of seven boxes (4 linear feet) of letters, notebooks, diaries, photograph albums and photos, ephemera, and newspapers and new clips pertaining to the lives of Jerome Beers Thomas, Jr., and his wife, Mary Denison (Wilt) Thomas. Boxes 1 through 5 are legal sized, Box 6 is regular sized, and Box 7 (newspapers) is a print box. Some photographs have nitrate negatives, and these have been removed to the nitrate negative file (File 192).
Most of the collection is devoted to the Thomas's stay in the Philippine Islands, 1900-1905, during Jerome Thomas's service as a U. S. Army surgeon, immediately after the Spanish-American War. The collection presents a clear and astute view of U.S.-Philippine relations during that period, as well as an informative and pictorial view of village life and the countryside in the hinterland of the Islands. It also reveals aspects of military operations in the Philippines during this period, which are not often the topics of studies or books.
A small portion of the collection is devoted to letters from a French family befriended by the Thomases in the years following World War I. Some memorabilia also remain on Camp Fremont (U.S. Army) in Palo Alto-Menlo Park, California, during World War I. In addition, a few letters from notables are in the collection (i. e., Jane Addams).
Container List
- Thomas Family Correspondence:, 1900-1965
  - Jerome B. Thomas, Letters to Family:, March-June 1900; (10 letters) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Life aboard a US Army transport. Descriptions of Gibralter, Malta, Suez Canal, Port Said, Ceylon, Manila, Angeles (PI.), General Leonard Wood. _._. Sprague, US Consul, Gibralter. Major General [William Dent] Grant. Philippine climate and disease.
  - Jerome B. Thomas, Letters to Family:, June-December 1900; (15 letters) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Descriptions of Philippine Islands; US Army Medical practice, Philippine Islands, during and after Spanish-American War (1898-1900). Apalit, Calumpit, Philippine Islands. US Commissioners for PI.: William Howard Taft, Henry Clay Ide, Bernard Moses.
  - Jerome B. Thomas, Letters to Family:, January-December 1901; (21 letters) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Apalit, Taglibaran, Lobac, PI. Manila (Army) Hospital No. 3. General Arthur MacArthur. General Fred[erick] Grant. Philippine Insurgents, [Emilio] Aquinaldo, Samson.
  - Jerome B. Thomas, Letters to Family:, January 1902-April 1903; (29 letters) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Taglibaran, Manila, Baguio, PI. Igarrotes. William Howard Taft (illness). Vice-governor [Luke] Wright, PI. [No further letters by JBT for 1903]
  - Jerome B. Thomas, Letters to Family:, January 1904-February 1905; (28 letters) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Manila and Baguio, PI. Governor [Luke] Wright. Vice Governor [Henry] Ide. US Commissioner Cameron Forbes. USS Korea v. Russian Squadron. Igarrotes. Benguet Road [PI.] Edwin Hurd Conger (US Minister to China).
  - Correspondence, Philippine Officials to Jerome B. Thomas:, 1901-1903; [in Spanish] (9 documents) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Street named for JB Thomas, request for JBT's continued presence, invitation to a church dedication.
  - Jerome B. Thomas Letters To/From US Government Officials:, 1940-1941; (11 letters) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mary Denison Wilt Thomas, Letters to Family:, April-July 1900; (11 letters-some duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    USS Hancock, Army Transport. Hong Kong. Angeles, and Apalit, PI. William Howard Taft.
  - Denison W. Thomas, Letters to Family:, July-December 1900; (15 letters-some duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Apalit PI., village life. Aguinaldo, General Buencamino.
  - Denison W. Thomas, Letters to Family:, January-June 1901; (12 letters-some duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Apalit, Manila, PI. Insurgent Aguinaldo, Buencamino, Arnedo.
  - Denison W. Thomas, Letters to Family:, July-October 1901; (11 letters-some duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Taglibaran, PI. Village life of US medical man and family in Philippines. Descriptions of locale and natives.
  - Denison W. Thomas, Letters to Family:, November-December 1901; (14 letters-some duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Village life. Insurgents Aguinaldo and Buencamino.
  - Denison W. Thomas, Letters to Family:, January 1902-June 1904 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Taglibaran and Baguio, PI. Philippine society.
  - Miscellaneous Drafts and Notes:, c1900-1905; (9 items) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence to Thomas Family from Friends in the Philippine Islands:, 1905-1907; (6 letters and cards) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence to Thomas Family from Worcester Family, PI:, 1919, 1931; (3 letters and cards) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    (see also Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Letter from Jane Addams to Denison Thomas:, December 2, 1911; (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    (83-57)
  - Letter from Ellen Coit Elliott to Denison Thomas:, April 1, 1953; (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    (83-58)
  - Postcard from Edna [?] to Denison Thomas:, August 8, 1912; (1 postcard) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    (83-59)
  - Correspondence to Denison Thomas from Family DeBrun:, 1919-1920; [in French] (18 letters and photos), (Box 1, Folder 20)
    (83-60)
  - Correspondence to Denison Thomas from Family DeBrun:, 1922-1927; [in French] (16 letters, some photos) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cards to the Thomas Family from Relatives and Stanford University Friends, (3 items) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Christmas card to Dr. and Mrs. Jerome Thomas from Mr. & Mrs. Yvor Winters. Photograph of art work by Tomita Pena, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    (84-012)
- Diaries, Notebooks, Reports, Sketches
  - Diary, Denison W. Thomas, PI.:, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    (and 1 page of Diary, PI. 1904)
  - Notes on Philippine Islands by Denison Thomas:, 1900-1905? (Box 2, Folder 2)
    (handwritten) n.d. (? pages)
  - Notebook, Denison W. Thomas:, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Accounts Notebook, Denison W. Thomas, PI:, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    (83-56)
  - Notebook, Denison W. Thomas:, 1913-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, Denison W. Thomas:, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reports on Civil Sanitarium, Baguio, PI:, 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    1. Report on Civil Sanitarium (3 pages) to the Secretary of the Interior, by Jerome B. Thomas.
    2. Printed Circular on Civil Sanitarium, Baguio, PI.: 1903. (4 pages)
  - Reports on Benguet Road [Baguio]:, 1903; (16 pages) (Folder 8)
    1. By Major McKennon.
    2. Building of the Benguet Road by Arthur Page (? pages)
  - Weather Reports, Baguio, PI:, 1904; (4 reports) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Report on Mirador Observatory [Weather], Baguio, PI:, 1909; (20 pages) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Philippine Island Maps:, 1900-1905? (Box 2, Folder 11)
    1. Baguio to Bontoc
    2. Cervantes to Sagrada (elev.) (Hand-drawn) (2 pages)
  - Miscellaneous WWI and Belgian War Relief Committee:, 1916-1918; (12 items) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    See also Box 7.
  - Philippine Independence Question:, 1916; (3 news clips) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Report on the Fauna of Rancho, La Brea, Part I: Occurrence, by JC Merriam, Berkeley, CA., 1911; (24 pages) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Report on the Fauna of Rancho, La Brea, Part II: Canidae, by JC Merriam, Berkeley, CA., 1911; (50 pages) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Report on the Fossils of the Pleistocene, Rancho La Brea, Berkeley, CA., 1911; (2 Reports) (19 pages) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Plot-Plan Map of Oakland, California:, 1912; (1 sheet) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Report on Glacial Land Forms in the Sierra Nevada: South of Lake Tahoe, by Wellington Jones, Berkeley, CA., 1929; (157 pages) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Report on Pleistocene Life, Rancho, La Brea: by Chester Stock, Los Angeles, CA., 1930; (82 pages) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Woman's City Club Magazine, San Francisco:, March 1938; (31 pages) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Pen and Ink Sketch Book, PI, Denison W. Thomas:, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Watercolor Sketch, Old Sugar Mill at Apalit, Denison W. Thomas, PI., 1900; (1 sheet) (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Sketch Book, Denison W. Thomas, PI:, 1901-1905 (Box 3)
- Sketches and Photographs
  - Pen and Ink Sketches, Denison W. Thomas, Taglibaran, PI:, 1901; (2 sheets) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Pen and Ink Sketches, Denison W. Thomas:, 1900s; (2 sketches) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Albums, Life in the Philippines,:, 1900; (2 albums) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Photos by Denison W. and Jerome B. Thomas. William Howard Taft, Bernard Moses, Don Juan Blanco, Dr. Jerome B. Thomas and Mrs. Denison W. Thomas, Macabebe Scouts.
  - Photo Album, Philippine Islands:, 1900-1903 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photo Album, Philippine Islands, Recuerdo:, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photo Album, Philippine Islands, Benguet Series:, 1903-1905? (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photo Album, Philippine Islands, n.d.:, 1900-1905? (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Photo Albums and Photographs
  - Photo Album, Camp Hay, Philippine Islands:, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mounted Photos, Philippine Islands, by J.B. Thomas:, 1900-1905; (9 photos) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mounted Photos, Philippine Islands:, 1900-1905; (21 photos) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Mounted Photos, Philippine Islands:, 1900-1905; (18 photos-some labeled) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mounted Photo, Water Buffalo, n.d., (1 photo) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Views of Manila and Angeles, PI., n.d., (9 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    (Nitrate Negatives removed to Nitrate Negative File, Photo 192)
  - 6 Views of Taglibaran, PI., n.d., (6 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Panorama View, Baguio, PI:, 1902? (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Government Center, Baguio, PI:, 1902?; (10 photos) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Views, Baguio, PI., n.d., (55 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Baguio landscapes and buildings.
  - Miscellaneous Views, Baguio, PI:, 1902-1904; (35 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Mrs. Kelly's school, houses (Nitrate Negatives removed to Nitrate File, Photo 192)
  - Philippine Natives:, 1900-1904; (75 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Philippine Villages, Natives and Flora:, 1900-1905; (45 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Views, PI.:, 1900-1905?; (17 loose photos-unlabeled) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Philippine Personalities:, 1900-1905; (6 loose photos) _, (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Buencamino, Otto Scherer, Mateo Cariño. (see also Box 4, Folder 4)
  - US Army Troops, PI.:, 1900-1905; (7 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Philippine Flora and Landscapes:, 1900-1905?; (9×12 in.) (5 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - View from Pali, Honolulu:, 1900?; (1 loose photo) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Women of Port Said:, 1900?; (1 loose photo) (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Fleet Entering Suez Canal:, 1900?; (1 loose photo) (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Temple, n.d., (1 loose photo-unlabeled) (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Native Village:, 1900-1905?; (1 loose photo-unlabeled) (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Colombo, Ceylon:, 1900?; (2 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Kuan Yin, n.d., (8×10 in.) (1 loose photo) (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Worcester Family and House, PI:, (11 loose photos) (Box 5, Folder 25)
    (see also Box 1, Folder 16) (Nitrate Negatives removed to Nitrate Negative File, Photo 192)
  - Tinted Postcards, Philippine Islands:, 1917; (7 postcards) (Box 5, Folder 26)
    (Nitrate Negatives removed to Nitrate Negative Tile, Photo 192)
  - Stereoptican Slides of Germany:, 1900s?; (6 mounted photos) (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous Photos and Postcards, California, n.d., (4 photos, 6 postcards) (Box 5, Folder 28)
    (Nitrate Negatives removed to Nitrate File, Photo 192)
  - Miscellaneous Envelopes (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Diary and Thomas Ephemera
  - Diary, Mercy Brett, Volumes I and II:, 1903-1904 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    (contains photos also)
  - Diary, Mercy Brett, Volume III:, 1904-1905 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Thomas Family Ephemera (boxed) (13 items)
  - Horsehair from Moro Pony (Box 6, Folder 3)
- 17 Newspapers and News clips, Philippine Islands and US papers, 1899-1957 (Box 7)
  (includes 6 articles in the newspaper (Dayton, Ohio) by Denison Thomas on the Philippines)